Finding Aid for the S. Charles Lee papers LSC.1384
UCLA Library Special Collections
- Photographs
  - Theatres
    - Fox Long Beach Theatre (West Coast Theatre). - Long Beach, 1931; Auditorium, lantern (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Lee's design for the ceiling lanterns incorporates traditional motifs such as fleurs-de-lys and sunbursts, while using sharp-edged geometry borrowed from Art Deco motifs.
    - Fox Long Beach Theatre (West Coast Theatre). - Long Beach, 1931; Foyer (Box 2, Folder 12)
      The foyer is low-ceilinged and relatively narrow. It serves primarily as access to the balcony. The pylons atop the newel posts echo the giant pylons on the façade. The coffered and stenciled ceiling is a scaled-down version of the auditorium ceiling.
    - Fox Long Beach Theatre (West Coast Theatre). - Long Beach, 1931; Auditorium detail (Box 2, Folder 12)
      Larger-than-life sculptures of women representing comedy and tragedy flank the stage; such representations are common motifs in theatre design. Both the statues and the surrounding columns are of cast stone. The columns are painted to simulate marble.
    - Fox Long Beach Theatre (West Coast Theatre). - Long Beach, 1931; Auditorium rear (Box 2, Folder 12)
      This view shows the lower and upper balconies. The side walls were painted to simulate masonry with superimposed pilasters. Lee designed unusual indirect lighting fixtures and shades for the ceiling, side walls and under the balcony.
    - Fox Long Beach Theatre (West Coast Theatre). - Long Beach, 1931; Mezzanine (Box 2, Folder 12)
      The mezzanine floor offers access to the lower balcony and stairs lead up to the upper balcony. The vaulted ceiling features stenciled beams with some arches filled in with stenciled garlands reminiscent of designs by Adams. Settees and chairs reflect the scale of the building.
    - Fox Phoenix Theatre. - Phoenix, 1930-1931; Ladies' lounge (Box 2, Folder 13)
      In the ladies' lounge, Lee scaled down the furniture and used curves and rounded edges. Individual vanities with shelves, seats and mirrors were typical of large motion picture theatres of the period. The bouquet of flowers on the table indicates that the photograph was taken at the time of the opening.
    - Fox Phoenix Theatre. - Phoenix, 1930-1931; Auditorium,balcony (Box 2, Folder 13)
      On this wall an archer takes aim at a gazelle, while birds fly overhead. Jewel-like lanterns composed of geometrically shaped glass panes hang from the ceiling.
    - Fox Phoenix Theatre. - Phoenix, 1930-1931; Box office, lobby (Box 2, Folder 13)
      Lee's design for the lobby, with the sunburst design on the terrazzo floor, repeated in the ceiling lights, the gilded zig-zag chevron motifs over the doors and the heavy gilded ornament of the box office illustrates his motto: The show started on the sidewalk.
    - Fox Phoenix Theatre. - Phoenix, 1930-1931; Auditorium, proscenium (Box 2, Folder 13)
      The walls and ceiling are decorated with swirling Art Deco and Zig-Zag motifs, accented by a pair of leaping mythical gazelles above the proscenium. Above them a gilded sunburst spreads out over the ceiling, an ornament incorporating the air intake grille of the ventilation system. The fire curtain displays an abstracted version of the Arizona desert landscape. Gilded grilles echoing the design of the box office and topped by sunbursts flank the proscenium above the front exits. The theatre organ, to accompany silent motion pictures, is at the front of the auditorium.
    - Fox Phoenix Theatre. - Phoenix, 1930-1931; Construction (Box 2, Folder 13)
      This photograph of the theatre under construction shows the auditorium space offset to the left, belying the symmetry of the façade.
    - Fox Phoenix Theatre. - Phoenix, 1930-1931; Auditorium pylon detail (Box 2, Folder 13)
      This photograph shows the base of one of the cast stone auditorium pilasters before installation.
    - Fox Phoenix Theatre. - Phoenix, 1930-193; Lounge (Box 2, Folder 13)
      In the commodious upstairs lounge, Lee repeated the sunburst motif in the doors to the men's and ladies' rooms. A drinking fountain set into a marble niche was framed by an abstract fountain design painted on the wall. Sculptures of rearing horses set on the tables introduce a Western theme. The large-scale furnishings with their angular forms are similar to those in the foyer.
    - Fox Phoenix Theatre. - Phoenix, 1930-1931; Facade (Box 2, Folder 13)
      The Fox Phoenix Theatre of 1930-1931 was one of Lee's largest and most elaborate creations. Designed in the sharp-edged, abstract Zig-Zag Moderne style, the building covered half of one of Phoenix's giant city blocks and had retail shop fronts at the sidewalk. Colored translucent glass in an Art Deco design decorated the transoms above the display windows. The auditorium is offset to the left behind the symmetrical façade. The foyer is in the interior of the building. A vertical neon sign mounted on the central pylon above the marquee advertises the theatre, while a temporary sign on the marquee advertises a cool interior, an important advantage in Phoenix's desert climate.
    - Fox Phoenix Theatre. - Phoenix, 1930-1931; Mezzanine ? (Box 2, Folder 13)
      The foyer ceiling is decorated with large-scale Art Deco designs abstracted from leaf, flower, sun and wave forms. The arched ceiling is squared off and accentuated by wooden moldings forming broad ribs. Furniture, mirror and lights are all squared off with cut corners, contrasting with the curving forms painted on the ceiling. Even the carpet design exhibits angular diagonals.
    - Fox Phoenix Theatre. - Phoenix, 1930-1931; Auditorium, side wall (Box 2, Folder 13)
      Mythical gazelle-like creatures romp in the abstract landscape decorating the auditorium walls. Sunbursts top the scalloped border of the scene at the top of the wall. Angular pilasters interrupt the wall surface; they probably house ventilation or sound ducts.
    - Fox Phoenix Theatre. - Phoenix, 1930-1931; Construction site (Box 2, Folder 13)
      A photograph of the construction site shows the extent of the theatre in relationship to nearby buildings and the surrounding low-rise urban context.
    - Fox Phoenix Theatre. - Phoenix, 1930-1931; Foyer stair (Box 2, Folder 13)
      The most striking feature of the foyer is the dramatic curving staircase to the lounge and balcony. Slender metal poles topped with glass disks and globes accentuate the curving form that appears to float in the space, outlined by the delicate filigree of the metal railing.
    - Fox Redondo Theatre. - Redondo Beach, 1937-1939; Perspective sketch, variant design (Box 2, Folder 14)
      In this concept drawing, Lee proposes another more elaborate Streamline Moderne design for the Fox Redondo Beach remodel.
    - Fox Redondo Theatre. - Redondo Beach, 1937-1939; Exterior before remodel (Box 2, Folder 14)
      The old Fox Redondo Beach theatre was slated for a remodel and Lee presented two concepts. This photo shows the building to be remodeled. Written on back of photo: Theatre as it appears from main business section of Redondo.
    - Fox Redondo Theatre. - Redondo Beach, 1937-1939; Perspective sketch, hand-colored (Box 2, Folder 14)
      Restyled as the Vogue Theatre, this concept replaces the previous Spanish Colonial Revival façade with a Streamline Moderne design current in the late 1930s.
    - Fox Theatre. - Bakersfield, 1929-1930; Perspective sketch (Box 2, Folder 15)
      Lee's concept for the Fox Theatre in Bakersfield envisioned a major retail center anchored by the theatre on the corner and advertised by a multi-story tower rising at the corner. Designed in the Spanish Colonial Revival style, the building featured a series of arcades at street level, mission tile on the roof, white stucco walls, and elaborate Churrigueresque detailing in cast stone on the tower, especially around the tower windows.
    - Fox Theatre. - Bakersfield, 1929-1930; Auditorium (Box 2, Folder 15)
      The auditorium is a so-called atmosphere theatre, a popular design type which created a stage set surrounding the audience. In this example, the auditorium simulates a Spanish Colonial Revival village into which the audience enters to see the show. Simulated buildings project from the walls, ivy hangs from their balconies and windows, trees painted on the wall behind provide a natural setting, and the whole is illuminated to create a realistic effect. Above is the dark sky, painted with clouds and featuring twinkling lights simulating the stars.
    - Fox Theatre. - Bakersfield, 1929-1930; Exterior (publication) (Box 2, Folder 15)
      Considerably simplified and scaled down, the finished theatre retained its tower and some of the Churrigueresque detailing around the two lower tower windows. The square tower features a clock at the top. The stark poured concrete building maximizes the square footage of the lot. The marquee and arcade at street level and the curvilinear gable and balcony on the left wall relieve the severity of the design.
    - Fox Theatre. - Bakersfield, 1929-1930; Stair (Box 2, Folder 15)
      Massive arches and stenciled decoration on the staircase walls carry out the Spanish Colonial Revival theme.
    - Fox Theatre. - Bakersfield, 1929-1930; Foyer (Box 2, Folder 15)
      Dramatic sloping beams (in poured concrete) stenciled in geometric designs enliven the foyer.
    - Fox Theatre. - Bakersfield, 1929-1930; Foyer, tapestry (Box 2, Folder 15)
      Tapestries depicting a map (right) and the Conquistadores encountering Native Americans decorate the foyer walls.
    - Fox Westwood Theatre. (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Fox Wilshire Theatre. - Beverly Hills, 1928-1930; Foyer, perspective sketch (Box 3, Folder 1)
      The concept for the foyer proposed a domed ceiling, executed perhaps in stained glass or in paint on plaster. Curved staircases lead to the mezzanine above.
    - Fox Wilshire Theatre. - Beverly Hills, 1928-1930; Detail (Box 3, Folder 1)
      This abstract floral and leaf design executed in cast stone was probably part of a screen over a ventilation or sound duct at the side of the proscenium arch.
    - Fox Wilshire Theatre. - Beverly Hills, 1928-1930; Ladies' lounge (Box 3, Folder 1)
      For the ladies' lounge, Lee used reflective black wall surfaces, angular mirrors, a white ceiling and zig-zag shaped vanity lights to create the glamorous sophisticated look associated with Hollywood in the 1920s.
    - Fox Wilshire Theatre. - Beverly Hills, 1928-1930; Exterior, interiors (publication) (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Four photographs published at the time of the opening show the mezzanine, (top right), the exterior (center), the foyer (lower left), and the auditorium (lower right).
    - Fox Wilshire Theatre. - Beverly Hills, 1928-1930; Construction, May 8, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      The angular-shaped tower dominates the already completed walls of the auditorium and stage flies.
    - Fox Wilshire Theatre. - Beverly Hills, 1928-1930; Exterior night (Box 3, Folder 1)
      The Fox Wilshire on opening night illuminated by spotlights and draped with bunting. The exterior design was a much simplified version of Lee's many concepts. The Fox sign became the most prominent attribute of the tower at night.
    - Fox Wilshire Theatre. - Beverly Hills, 1928-1930; Construction, February 27, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      This construction photo shows the basement and the mass of wood framing used to make the forms for the poured concrete. The large derrick in the background was used to lift the materials and equipment up as the building rose.
    - Fox Wilshire Theatre. - Beverly Hills, 1928-1930; Auditorium, proscenium (Box 3, Folder 1)
      The stage curtain panels in another possible configuration.
    - Fox Wilshire Theatre. - Beverly Hills, 1928-1930; Auditorium, proscenium (Box 3, Folder 1)
      The stage opening is set back deeply into a much larger proscenium arch. The sloping walls and ceiling surrounding the stage are heavily ornamented in gilt or silver plaster relief; the forms are the abstracted designs from nature and geometry typical of Art Deco design. The stage curtain was designed in separate panels that could be raised individually to adjust the space to stage productions or motion picture screenings while introducing a dramatic design element at the same time.
    - Fox Wilshire Theatre. - Beverly Hills, 1928-1930; Construction, March 27, 1930 (Box 3, Folder 1)
      Here, two derricks are operating as the building rises on the corner of Wilshire Boulevard.
    - Fox Wilshire Theatre. - Beverly Hills, 1928-1930; Auditorium, perspective sketch (Box 3, Folder 1)
      The interior design concept was in lavish Art Deco with contrasting light and dark (probably black and silver or gilt).
    - Fox Wilshire Theatre. - Beverly Hills, 1928-1930; Auditorium, proscenium (Box 3, Folder 1)
      The stage curtain in place for motion picture screening.
    - Fox Wilshire Theatre. - Beverly Hills, 1928-1930; Exterior renderings (publication) (Box 3, Folder 1)
      This publication shows three of Lee's many concepts for this lavish and important building in Beverly Hills. The building opened on September 19, 1930, only weeks before the stock market crash. Several sketches for the landmark tower survive in the Lee collection.
    - Fremont Theatre. - San Luis Obispo., 1941-1942 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Garmar Theatre. - Montebello, 1949-1950; Perspective sketch (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Garmar Theatre. - Montebello, 1949-1950; Entrance, marquee (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Garmar Theatre. - Montebello, 1949-1950; Auditorium (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Garmar Theatre. - Montebello, 1949-1950; Crying room (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Garmar Theatre. - Montebello, 1949-1950; Projection room (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Gentry Theatre. - Compton., 1937 (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Grand Theatre. - Clarkdale Arizona, 1936; Handwritten note on reverse (Box 3, Folder 5)
      Correspondence.
    - Grand Theatre. - Clarke?dale Arizona, 1936; Collage, exterior and interior (Box 3, Folder 5)
      This 250 seat theatre for the United Verde Copper company in Clarkdale, Arizona was probably Lee's simplest design and smallest commission. The crowd of people in front of the theatre, the handwritten note on the reverse of the picture, and the letter from the theatre manager all attest to the appreciation of this small theatre in a remote town in northern Arizona.
    - Grand Theatre. - Clarkdale Arizona, 1936; Pencil note on reverse (Box 3, Folder 5)
      Two ceiling fans, some benches painted red and a crying room were all features added to this little theatre.
    - Grand Theatre. - Clarkdale Arizona, 1936; Letter to SCL, typescript (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Grand Theatre. - Clarkdale Arizona, 1936; Letter from Joe Becchetti, December 18, 1936 (Box 3, Folder 5)
    - Harper Grand Theatre. - Fontana., 1948 (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Helix Theatre. - La Mesa, 1947-1948; Exterior, entry doors (Box 3, Folder 7)
      The design evolved into a storefront remodel using every device to capture attention from the passerby. The strong diamond pattern applied to the upper story, the series of vertical posts applied at street and the paneled entry doors draw attention to the centerpiece, the curving neon-outlined marquee. A curved box office at the sidewalk and poster cases framed in wavey edged box frames are overwhelmed by the other design elements. Here, the chief purpose of the design is to draw attention to the storefront by using a variety of cheap applied elements without regard for design integration.
    - Helix Theatre. - La Mesa, 1947-1948; Perspective sketch variant (Box 3, Folder 7)
      A later concept drawing shows a scaled-down design which is more conventional in massing. Streamline forms can still be seen in the sign area and in the porthole window on the right wall. However, the chief design elements have evolved from the smooth to the angular with walls, marquee and canopies project out and up at angles.
    - Helix Theatre. - La Mesa, 1947-1948; Perspective sketch (Box 3, Folder 7)
      This concept drawing, probably executed before World War II, uses simple curved forms of Streamline Moderne in the building. A huge sign with a spiral or helix-shaped tower dominates the façade.
    - Hippodrome Theatre, Perspective sketch (Box 3, Folder 8)
      Put this with 50401-50408. A discussion of these various concepts will pull these images together.
    - Hollywood Theatre. - Hollywood, 1936; Facade (Box 3, Folder 9)
      This modest remodel of a storefront theatre replaced an earlier remodel of 1927 on a commercial building dating from 1919. The storefront tenants are all theatre-related, a restaurant where theatre patrons can eat before the show, a popcorn shop, a candy store for candy to take into the show and a bookstore to browse in while waiting for the show to start. The neon-lit marquee and the tall neon sign attached to the parapet draw attention to the theatre entrance.
    - Hopkins Theatre. - Oakland, 1938-1941; Perspective sketch (Box 3, Folder 10)
      This elaborate concept drawing shows a Streamline Moderne design using convex and concave curves, a prow-shaped pylon, and angular massing.
    - Hopkins Theatre. - Oakland, 1938-1941; Facade (Box 3, Folder 10)
      As built, the theatre was a much simplified Streamline Moderne façade overlaid on a basic brick commercial building. Strong contrasts between black and white and streams of neon outlining the marquee draw attention to the building.
    - Hopkins Theatre. - Oakland, 1938-1941; Auditorium (Box 3, Folder 10)
      The simple interior design illustrates the Streamline theme with the use of painted curves on the walls and semicircular ceiling panels that conceal lights, creating indirect lighting of the ceiling. Instead of a balcony, the rear of the auditorium is raked and separated from the main floor by a low partition and steps.
    - Huntridge Theatre. (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Iris Theatre - Hollywood. (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Huntridge Theatre. - Las Vegas Nevada, 1943; Perspective sketch (Box 3, Folder 11)
      Lee recycled this design for his proposed concept for the Lakewood Theatre in Lakewood, California.
    - Iris Theatre - Hollywood. (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Ken Theatre. - San Diego., ca. 1950 (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Kinema Theatre. - Los Angeles, 1917, 1931; Remodel 1931 (1917 building). (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - La Reina Theatre. - Sherman Oaks., 1937-1938 (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - La Tijera Theatre. - Los Angeles, 1948-1949; Exterior day (Box 3, Folder 16)
      In the late 1940s and 1950s architects combined the fluid forms of the Streamline Moderne style with the square modules favored by International Style architects. In California, a new form of architectural modernism was developing that favored the use of natural materials, especially stone and wood, foremost in residential building. These influences, however, were also felt in commercial buildings, especially in the suburbs. Hence La Tijera Theatre, on Sepulveda Boulevard in a growing suburban area near the airport. A streamlined automobile can be seen entering the porte-cochere on the left.
    - La Tijera Theatre. - Los Angeles, 1948-1949; Exterior night (Box 3, Folder 16)
      Lee designed his theatres to be most effective at night. The tall neon sign seems to hang in the air above the building. A grid of round lights underneath the canopy forms a high marquee and illuminates the entrance. Translucent panels on the lobby walls glow invitingly and the aluminum frames reflect the light. The poster cases are illuminated internally and outlined by neon strips.
    - La Tijera Theatre. - Los Angeles, 1948-1949; Ladies' lounge (Box 3, Folder 16)
      Round stools and round mirrors at the vanity counter and a curved banquette fitted to the curved wall of the ladies' lounge reinforce the Streamline look. Even the wallpaper, printed with a pattern of round tents, echoes the theme.
    - La Tijera Theatre. - Los Angeles, 1948-1949; Foyer, popcorn counter (Box 3, Folder 16)
      A mural on the slanting and curved wall of the foyer depicts a workman carrying a heavy basket (of sugar cane?) and a woman kneeling, both in a tropical setting.
    - La Tijera Theatre. - Los Angeles, 1948-1949; Auditorium (Box 3, Folder 16)
      The auditorium walls curve towards the screen, interrupted in each side a scalloped wall edge where the screen curtain lit by indirect lighting begins. The effect is further enhanced by the continuation of a vine pattern on the walls in cut-out form over the front exit openings. Globes of light at the center of grilles concealing the ceiling fans neatly combine two functions. The ceiling is further decorated by a scalloped design painted around the light and ventilation fixtures.
    - La Tijera Theatre. - Los Angeles, 1948-1949; Foyer, view out to street (Box 3, Folder 16)
      Two-story floor-to-ceiling windows illuminate the foyer.
    - La Tijera Theatre. - Los Angeles, 1948-1949; Perspective sketch (Box 3, Folder 16)
      Lee's concept combines the flowing forms of Streamline Moderne, still considered the height of modernism, with the square modules and slim brick rectangular pylon borrowed from the International Style.
    - La Tijera Theatre. - Los Angeles, 1948-1949; Foyer, bas relief (Box 3, Folder 16)
      A curved banquette flanks the candy counter and popcorn machine. Bouquets of flowers on the shelf above the banquette indicate the photo was taken on opening night.
    - Lakewood Theatre. - Lakewood, 1944-1945; Auditorium, proscenium (Box 3, Folder 17)
      The typical proscenium arch has been dispensed with, although it is still indicated by the swags of the valance and the curtain before the screen. Decoration is minimal and concentrates solely on the curved portion of the side walls flanking the screen.
    - Lakewood Theatre. - Lakewood, 1944-1945; Foyer (Box 3, Folder 17)
      Sleek banquettes upholstered in a striped fabric are set into the walls of the foyer. An overhanging cornice creates the opportunity to conceal indirect lighting and reduces the space to a human scale. A narrow screen pierced by square, framed cut-outs is located at the end of the banquette, enhancing a sense of enclosure.
    - Lakewood Theatre. - Lakewood, 1944-1945; Foyer (Box 3, Folder 17)
      As the theatre was a re-use of an earlier building, Lee had little opportunity for interior structural changes. For the foyer, Lee chose modern, rectangular lines. Paneled auditorium doors and the simplified Greek key design painted on the upper wall add interest.
    - Lakewood Theatre. - Lakewood, 1944-1945; Exterior (Box 3, Folder 17)
      Lee's design was adapted to remodeling the old Town Hall on the site. The pylon with its scalloped sides and the marquee are the only design elements on the exterior.
    - Lakewood Theatre. - Lakewood, 1944-1945; Auditorium, sidewall (Box 3, Folder 17)
      Abstract metal sculptures evoking a pineapple ornament the side walls. Their reflective surfaces and the wavy reflective stripes behind them give a touch of elegance of Regency Moderne to the otherwise utilitarian auditorium.
    - Lakewood Theatre. - Lakewood, 1944-1945; Perspective sketch variant (Box 3, Folder 17)
      This later rendering was far more streamlined than the earlier version with curving walls, porthole openings and prow-like pylons. The airplane flying overhead reinforces the streamlined imagery.
    - Lakewood Theatre. - Lakewood, 1944-1945; Lee, opening night (Box 3, Folder 17)
      At opening night ceremonies, Lee (at left), holds a bouquet of roses together with a woman, probably the client's wife. Man at right is unidentified.
    - Lakewood Theatre. - Lakewood, 1944-1945; Perspective sketch (Box 3, Folder 17)